<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some seasonable remarks upon the deplorable fall of the Emperour Julian with an epistle of his to the citizens of Bostra / now made English ; by Philaretus Anthropopolita.</title>
            <author>Philaretus Anthropopolita.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11942219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11942219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51288</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 513:52)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some seasonable remarks upon the deplorable fall of the Emperour Julian with an epistle of his to the citizens of Bostra / now made English ; by Philaretus Anthropopolita.</title>
                  <author>Philaretus Anthropopolita.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Gellibrand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Julian, --  Emperor of Rome, 331-363.</term>
               <term>Church and state.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Some Seaſonable REMARKS Upon the Deplorable Fall OF THE EMPEROUR
JULIAN, With an EPISTLE of his TO THE CITIZENS of <hi>BOSTRA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now made ENGLISH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PHILARET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ANTHROPOPOLITA.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Caeterum intra Eccleſiam poteſtates neceſſariae non
eſſent, niſi ut quod non praevalent Sacerdotes efficere per Doctrinae
Sermonem Poteſtas haec impetret per Diſciplinae terrorem.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Major de Geſtis Scotorum, Lib. III. Cap.
XV.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Gellibrand,</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51288:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51288:2"/>
            <head>Some Seaſonable REMARKS Upon the deplorable Fall of the
Emperour JULIAN.</head>
            <p>HAd not our Holy Religion degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated much from its Native
good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the integrity in which our Saviour Jeſus and his bleſſed
Followers left it, it would have been indeed admirable that any once
inſtructed in it, and much more ſo excellent a perſon as <hi>Julian,</hi>
ſhould ever deſert it. For men of wild and extravagant tempers, and wholly
unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſolid Philoſophie and good reaſon, of which our
preſent Age too much abounds, to be eaſily ſeduc'd by our Modern Revivers
of the Epicurean folly, is no more ſtrange, than that all Brutal Natures are
prone to follow their untam'd inclinations: but for a perſon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely
Vertuous, profoundly Speculative, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably Learned and Eloquent, and (which
is yet more) firm and poſitive in the belief of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51288:3"/> Deity, and future life, to relinquiſh a
Religion of ſo much genuine Piety, and ſimple inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence as ours is, for
the fond Superſtitions of Heathens and groſs Idolaters, would be not only
unaccountable, but above meaſure ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious, did we not find the
lamentable cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it in the debaucht Chriſtianity of thoſe times; I
mean the times of the two Emperours, <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and
<hi>Conſtantius;</hi> for then firſt our Religion was converted into
Faction, Policie, and vile Hypocriſie. Till then, Chriſts faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Followers had learnt no other Leſſons than thoſe of Faſting, Praying,
Mortifying the Fleſh, Patient and humble ſuffering, mutual love and
forbearance, and living in common; the greateſt being not in Name, but
reality Servants to the meaneſt. But now having got Ambitious and
Diſſolute Princes of their Party, inſtead of teaching them their Vertues,
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves learnt their Vices. And now it was the voice was heard from
Heaven, <hi>Poiſon is fallen into the Church.</hi> But ſince I am fallen
upon the mention of that hard and ſowre word <hi>Church,</hi> I think it not
amiſs, nor impertinent to this place, to inſert a brief account of the
antient Diſcipline us'd among Chriſtians, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the corruption and
ambition of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51288:3"/> Clergy, the undoubted ſpawn of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, can
never well be diſcerned. Our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour Chriſt then having
publickly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> declared his <hi>Kingdom</hi> was
<hi>not of this world;</hi> and not only ſo, but refuſed to arbitrate
privately betwixt two Brothers, as being neither <hi>Judge</hi> nor
<hi>Divider</hi> among them; and having over and above this, ſtrictly
prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited any priority among his followers, and that not only by words, but
by wonderful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, himſelf condeſcending to the moſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
Office of waſhing their feet; cannot be ſuppoſed in contradiction to all
this, to have erected a Spiritual Juriſdiction, or a Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
Prieſts, empowr'd Arbitrarily to Enact Laws, and to force all Orders of men,
if once Chriſtians, to pay humble and implicite Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them; and this
upon pain of forfeiting their whole right to publick Reputation and Humane
Converſe, nay Religion, and Eternal Salvation it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Nor do we anywhere find in Scripture that he ever did <hi>de
facto</hi> inſtitute any Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, either by <hi>Biſhops,
Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> but of this ſee the excellent Author of
<hi>Irenicum,</hi> or <hi>Weaponſalve,</hi> at large. True in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he once
ſaid, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae, Tell the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51288:4"/> but thoſe are not words of Inſtitution, but
ſuppoſe that <hi>Convention</hi> already in being, as well as the
<hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. What
then ſhall we ſay? Muſt he not of neceſſity be ſuppoſed to have
directed his Diſciples to Aſſociate, as all other Sects of <hi>Jews</hi>
did, according to the Form of Politie then in uſe? Yes ſurely, if he was no
<hi>Judge</hi> nor <hi>Divider,</hi> nor had any <hi>Earthly Kingdom.</hi> Is
this my ſingle opinion, or doth not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Grotius</hi> upon
<hi>Acts</hi> 13. aſſert the ſame in theſe full words: <hi>Totum
regimen Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiarum Chriſti conformatum eſt ad Exemplar Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogarum.
The whole Government of Chriſts Churches was ſhap'd to the Model of the
Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues,</hi> or Moſaick Form of Politie. And certainly, had not this
been true, our Saviour would never have predicted it as one of the calamities
his faithful followers ſhould endure for his ſake, to be Expell'd the
Synagogues, but rather the contrary, to be forc'd to them.</p>
            <p>What theſe Synagogues were, is ſuperfluous to mention, ſince
the Learned ſo well know, that moſt of the Judicatures of thoſe antient
Nations, which we have any account of, were Conſecrated Temples, intended for
the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Divine and Humane Affairs joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51288:4"/> Such were the <hi>Roman Curiae,</hi> the
<hi>Athenian Areopagus,</hi> the <hi>Delphick Temple,</hi> the
<hi>Conventions</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and their Temple at
<hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> But the <hi>Iſraelitick Conventions,</hi> called in
Greek ſometime <hi>Synagogae,</hi> and ſometime <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi> were
made up of as many Freemen of their reſpective Burroughs, (for ſo the world
was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently model'd) as at the voice of a Cryer, or the winding of a Horn,
would aſſemble; the Town-Council call'd the <hi>Presbytery</hi> or
<hi>Senate,</hi> with their Chief, ever preſiding. This prime man, call'd in
<hi>Greek Archon, Archiſynagogus,</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopus,</hi> for ſo
(<hi>Judg.</hi> 9.28.) <hi>Zebul</hi> Mayor of <hi>Shechem</hi> is ſtiled by
the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> was to ſuperintend and manage the
<hi>Convention,</hi> and the <hi>Councel</hi> called <hi>Presbyters</hi> in
<hi>Greek,</hi> and in <hi>Latine Seniores,</hi> being men of Age, Gravity, and
Prudence, were to weigh and examine matters brought before them, and to direct
and adviſe the Commoners; and in fine, the whole Body or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
was to give Suffrage, and this in all Cauſes whatſoever, whether Sacred or
Civil, except ſome few, which being very weighty, were reſerved for the
Cognizance of the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phictyones</hi> of the Nation, I mean the Seventy two
wiſe Repreſentatives of the Tribes, called the <hi>Synedrion,</hi> or Grand
Council, who ſat in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51288:5"/> the Temple or Divine Oracle at
<hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> the Prieſts then making no diſtinct State from the
reſt, but Voting in common with others, whatever Figure any of them happened
to make, either in the <hi>Synedrion,</hi> or the leſſer
<hi>Conventions;</hi> their peculiar work being not Government, but
Sacrificing, &amp;c. But that the <hi>Synagogues</hi> were really Civil Courts,
is plain from thoſe many paſſages in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that mention
Trials in them for <hi>Adultery</hi> and other Crimes, as alſo the Apoſtles
being perſecuted and whipped in them; which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly could not have been,
if they had been meer Oratories like our Churches. But the Jewiſh ſtory of
<hi>Suſanna</hi> among our Apocryphal Books, puts the controverſie out of
all queſtion, which very well deſerves the peruſal; for though it be not
Divinely inſpired, yet it gives us a diſtinct and clear account of the
manner of Trials in thoſe antient <hi>Conventions.</hi> Now that the
<hi>Jews,</hi> of which the Chriſtians were a Sect, were ſo tenacious of
their antient Rights and Form of Politie, that they kept up in all their
Captivities and Peregrinations, their <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues</hi> or
<hi>Conventions,</hi> with the ſame zeal they maintain'd their Religion and
Rituals with, is ſo well known, that I need not here tell it.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51288:5"/> But being now under the Juriſdiction of other
Nations, and depriv'd of their <hi>Jura Majeſtatis,</hi> and ſo of the
cognizance of matters Capital by their Laws, they could not puniſh in any
caſe with Death, unleſs perchance ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times either by a particular
Licence or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance from their Superiours: To ſupply this neceſſary
defect, they were forc'd to have recourſe to <hi>Expulſion</hi> or
<hi>Baniſhment</hi> from their Community, with a Form of Imprecation, or
<hi>Anathema,</hi> whereby the Excommunicated was devoted to Divine Vengeance
and the fury of the Penal <hi>Daemons;</hi> a Cuſtome common to them with the
<hi>Athenians</hi> and antient <hi>Romans,</hi> who were wont to back all
ſuch Laws as they would have to be Sacred and Inviolable, with a dreadful
Curſe upon ſuch as ſhould preſume to break them, or ſhould break them
and yet eſcape publick Juſtice. <hi>Sacratae Leges</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Feſtus) ſunt quibus ſanctum eſt, qui quid ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus eas fecerit,
ſacer alicui Deorum ſit, cum familiâ pecuniâque. Laws made
Sacred are ſuch as have a Clauſe in them, Ordering that whoever ſhall do
any thing againſt them ſhall be Devoted to ſome one of the Gods, with his
Family and Goods.</hi> That what I have affirmed of the Jews, is not by mere
conjecture, I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51288:6"/> one clear Teſtimony, which our Learned
<hi>Selden</hi> quotes out of a Manuſcript, in his firſt Book <hi>De
Synedriis.</hi> The Author is one <hi>Elias ben Moſes,</hi> by Sect a
<hi>Carée</hi> or Scripturiſt, who ſpeaks of <hi>Benjamin ben
Moſes</hi> thus; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, <hi>Rabbi</hi> Benjamin ben
Moſes <hi>ſaid, That ſuch as had committed any foul Crime, or
tranſgreſs'd in any ſuch caſe as might not be puniſhed as the Law
required, in time of Captivity, was to repent and make his Submiſſion, with
a promiſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. But if he ſhould refuſe to promiſe Obedience
to the Divine Laws, we were to Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematize and Excommuicate him, as it is
writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> (Ezra 10.8.) <hi>His goods ſhall be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd, and
himſelf Excommunicated from the Cahal,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſia.</hi> Which
Text was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by our Tranſlators, nor by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, who is in the ſame errour with them. And that
this was put in practice by the Jews upon the Primitive Chriſtians, I
authentically prove by the Authority of St. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr</hi> in his
incomparable Dialogue with <hi>Tryphon</hi> the Jew. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
(ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51288:6"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. that is; <hi>And ſtill
you ſet at nought ſuch as confide in him, and in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and
Soveraign Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour that ſent him, and do what you are able to expoſe them;
while you curſe in your Synagogues thoſe that truſt in Chriſt. For you
have not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe your ſelves</hi> (mark) <hi>to become our Murderers,
becauſe of the preſent Powers: though as oft as you could, you have not
been ſparing in that too.</hi> This much I think is more than ſufficient to
evince the perfect conſent there was betwixt the Chriſtians and other
parties of Jews, in their Civil, or (if you will) Eccleſiaſtick
Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I know it will ſtill ſeem ſtrange to moſt,
whatever the <hi>Judaick</hi> Politie was, that the Chriſtian
<hi>Eccleſiae</hi> ſhould be accounted Popular, our Epiſcopiſts holding
them to have been a kinde of little Monarchies, and the Presbyterians
Ariſtocracies, I'll ſubjoyn a word or two of undeniable proof. Beſides
that, the Bleſſed Apoſtles, and the Holy Men of the Apoſtolick Age, St.
<hi>Clement,</hi> St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51288:7"/> St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> direct their Letters of
Inſtructions, for the moſt part, neither to one ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor yet
to a ſtinted number of people, but to whole <hi>Conventions:</hi> St.
<hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> chap. 5. expreſsly
charges them all <hi>in full Synagogue,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith he)
to deliver the inceſtuous perſon to Satan for his Correction, without once
mentioning the Clergy-man, or his Keys. Nay, (which is yet more) when the whole
Colledge of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were congregated at <hi>Hieruſalem, (Act.</hi> 15.)
to conſider the debates at <hi>Antioch</hi> about the <hi>Moſaick</hi>
Rituals, they preſume not to write in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Letters by their own
Authority, but regularly convene the People, and then make their ſeveral
Harangues to them. And (<hi>v.</hi> 22.) the Apoſtles, Presbyters, and the
whole <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> or <hi>Convention,</hi> paſs an order for the
draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of their ſenſe into the form of an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, which runs thus,
(<hi>v.</hi> 23.) <hi>The Apoſtles, Elders and Brethren,</hi> &amp;c. And
(<hi>v.</hi> 25.) its Authentickneſs is expreſſed thus,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>We thought fit in full Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. And
in fine, (<hi>v.</hi> 28.) <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to
us.</hi> By this may be ſeen, that in thoſe times the Holy Ghoſt was not
the Clergies peculiar, as it hath been
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51288:7"/> thought ſince, eſpecially by thoſe of
<hi>Simon</hi>'s trade. I'll adde the teſtimony of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in his
undoubted Epiſtle to the <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> becauſe he is commonly
thought a zealous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of the Clergie Intereſt. He there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades the
<hi>Convention</hi> to elect a Deacon for their Legate, to make a Viſit to
the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> to which he had belonged, in
theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you as a Convention of
God, to elect a Deacon to go as a Legate for God.</hi> And then addes,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. that is, <hi>It is no great matter, if you are but
willing to do ſo much for God, ſince your Neighbouring Conventions have
ſent ſome of them Biſhops, others Presbyters and Deacons.</hi> But if
none of this had been ſaid, it would be more than plain to every
unbyaſſed Reader of this good mans Epiſtles, that the Chriſtian Politie
was then rather faulty on the Popular ſide than otherwiſe; ſince ſo
many <hi>Conventions</hi> of Pious and Holy Men had ſo great need to be
inſtructed in their Duty of Subjection to their Biſhops and Presbyteries,
which, it ſhould ſeem, in thoſe good times was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51288:8"/> almoſt wholly neglected: it being, as the
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Commentary upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> (believed
to be St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s) informs us, <hi>Omnibus inter initia
conceſſum &amp; Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizare &amp; Baptizare, &amp; Scripturas in
Eccleſiâ explanare. Allowable for all Men at firſt to Preach,
Baptize, and Expound the Scriptures in the Convention.</hi> All which
<hi>Tertullian,</hi> no mean Authour in God's Church, aſſerts <hi>(in
Exhortat. ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor.)</hi> to be lawful ſtill, as to any thing of Divine
Right. <hi>Nonne &amp; Laici Sacerdotes ſumus? Scriptum eſt, Reges quoque
nos &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes Deo &amp; Patri ſuo fecit. Differentiam inter Ordinem
&amp; Plebem conſtituit Eccleſiae Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritas, &amp; honor per
conſeſſum ſanctificatus. Ideò ubi Eccleſiaſtici Ordinis non
eſt conſeſſus, &amp; offers &amp; tingis, &amp; Sacerdos es tibi
ſolus. Sed ubi tres, Eccleſia eſt, licet Laica.</hi> That is, <hi>Are not
we that are Laymen Prieſts too? It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, He hath made us Kings and
Prieſts to God and his Father. The diſtinction betwixt the Bench of
Presbyters and the Commoners, was made only for deference and reſpect to
thoſe that preſide in the Convention. Wherefore where there is not a
Convention-Bench thou thy ſelf giveſt the Euchariſt, Baptizeſt, and art
thine own Prieſt. Yet where there are three, there is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51288:8"/> a Convention, or Church, though but a Lay
one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt probable that the Diſorders, that continually
hapned in theſe Popular <hi>Churches,</hi> brought that Ariſtocracie, which
St. <hi>Hierome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Euagrius,</hi> and after him the
pious and learned Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> and the Modern Presbyterians plead
Preſcription for, as being much more antient than the preſent
Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy. However, it could not keep long from devolving into the
abſolute Power of Biſhops, who in proceſs of time were themſelves
alſo ſwallow'd up by Patriarchs, and all at laſt by one
<hi>Demogorgon</hi> Pope. In manner not unlike to this, the <hi>Roman</hi>
Senate too (to compare great things with ſmall) by trampling upon the poor
Plebeans, brought the Uſurper <hi>Caeſar,</hi> with a whole train of
Succeſſors, upon their own heads. This ſecond Alteration is noted, and
not without ſome ſeverity, by the antient Commentator upon the Firſt
Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> ſuppoſed to be the above-mentioned St.
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Milan; Et Synagoga</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp;

poſtea Eccleſia Seniores habuit, quorum ſine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio nihil agebatur;
quod quâ negligentiâ abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, neſcio; niſi fortè
Doctorum deſidiâ, aut magis ſuperbiâ, dum ſoli volunt aliquid
videri.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51288:9"/> That is, <hi>Both the Synagogue firſt</hi>
(mark the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) <hi>and the Church after, had its Seniours, which by what
neglect it hath come to be diſuſed, I know not; unleſs perchance through
the ſloath of Prelates, or (as I rather think) their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſeem
ſomebody alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more I might ſay, if my purpoſe were to be large; but
this much I could not omit, to ſhew by what ſteps the flock of Chriſt
came at laſt to be a prey to the Avarice and Ambition of Biſhops, in the
time of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Emperour <hi>Julian;</hi> in ſo much that they were
tamely led, or violently driven, like beaſts by Graziers, to fulfil the
brutiſh Paſſions and Intereſts of thoſe that managed them.</p>
            <p>To return to our firſt Diſcourſe then, this diſcerning
Prince ſoon ſaw their Deſigne was to erect in all parts of the Empire
their own <hi>Moſaick</hi> or Eccleſiaſtick Politie, by themſelves
Metamorphos'd from a Democracy into an Abſolute Tyranny: they having advanced
ſo far already, as to procure of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the ſole
Juriſdiction over Chriſtians, and leave to Aſſemble themſelves at
<hi>Nice,</hi> to divide the <hi>Roman</hi> Provinces among themſelves, and
make a new Body of Laws, called <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> to the
utter aboliſhing of the <hi>Roman</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51288:9"/> Laws and Government, and the great
Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of thoſe Gentiles whom God had not yet enlightned with his
Grace.</p>
            <p>He ſaw moreover that let a Chriſtian be never ſo deeply
Criminal, no profane hand muſt touch him; nor muſt he endure any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Puniſhment, than <hi>Confeſſion and Penance;</hi> and that when once
Abſolved, he was as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent as the unborn Child. Which practice of theirs
in proceſs of Time almoſt ruinated their Empire; For not reflecting, that
as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews and a conquered People, they had (as was above ſhew'd) been
deſpoiled of their <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Majeſtatis,</hi> and ſo of the uſe of the
Sword in caſes of Blood, it never came into their minds to petition
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> for the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their antient Rights; but
contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the perpetual practice of their Anceſtors, ſince
Chriſtianity only, held on in their now long-accuſtom'd track of
Anathematizing, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to have been of the ſame Divine Right with
their Religion; until at laſt, all men, good and bad, promiſcuouſly
crowding into the Church, to be of the Religion in vogue, they found their
Government become impracticable, and thereupon were forced to diſgorge what
they could not concoct, and to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51288:10"/> refund the cognizance of Capital and other
ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous matters to the old Pagan Civil Laws and Magiſtracy, which by this
means have been through God's Mercy continued down to our Times, where they
begin again to grow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant and to threaten Retaliation to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping
Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>Adde to this, that he could ſee no Perſon nor Rank exempted
from the dire <hi>Anathema</hi> Neither could he know, but that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
Prince himſelf might upon a Pique, ſuch as the diſgrace of a potent
Prelate, be on a ſudden Paganized, and next Aſſaſſinated even by them
that had advanc'd him, ſince he ſo lately ſaw <hi>Conſtans</hi> armed
againſt his own Brother <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> by the <hi>Roman</hi>
Biſhop and the great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> merely becauſe the latter had
been outed his See, though as ſome ſay, for Treaſon, Sorcery, and Murder.
And what indeed might he not juſtly fear, when he ſaw with what beſtial
Rage the ſeveral Factions the Biſhops form'd themſelves among the people,
by whom they were then Elected, did maſſacre each other. If a man, as
imagine it were at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> had a Deſigne to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant a more
potent and popular Competitor, no way ſo like to ruine him, as by giving out,

<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51288:10"/> that he was not a right Chriſtian, but a
cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter of the true Faith, for that he uſed to read <hi>Origen</hi> and
<hi>Plato,</hi> unſanctified Authors; and then ten to one but he was knockt
on the head, either by the Rabble of the Town, or by ſholes of
<hi>Anthropomorphite</hi> Monks, who commonly made what Biſhops they
pleaſed, and for a long time made a prey of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> Kingdome,
as well as of later years of our own; but now God hath delivered us, by the
means of a great and generous Prince, from this fort of <hi>Egyptian</hi>
Vermine, who reſtored our Religion to its Primitive Candour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity,
partly in his own Perſon, and partly by his Son and Daughter of Eternal
Memory, who obliged their Spiritual as well as Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Subjects to ſwear
Fealty to them, as their Eccleſiaſtick (ſince there muſt be that
diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) as well as Civil Supremes.</p>
            <p>But to return whence I diverted; I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded nothing
offended him ſo much, as the vile Hypocriſie of the then Clergy, who
beſides their coyning of contrary Creeds, in the Reigns of
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and modelling Religion by
Court-Intrigues, ſeemed almoſt wholly to diſpenſe with Morality,
placing Sanctimony not ſo much in a good Life, as in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51288:11"/> the ſtrict Obſervance of the Rituals and
the Symbolical Repreſentations of our Religion; ſuch as Baptiſm, the
Euchariſt, Chriſm, but above all in ſubmitting to the Formalities of
Confeſſion and Penance, upon which the worſt of offences were too
eaſily remitted. What fleſh could bear to hear the Murderers of ones
Father, Uncle, two Brothers, ſix Couſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germans, harangued to Heaven in
Pulpits, as very holy and good men, becauſe (forſooth) abſolved by their
own Friends the Prieſts? And I the rather ſuſpect this to have been the
principal Cauſe of his Tragical Apoſtacy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I do not finde his
Satyr any where ſo truculent, as upon this occaſion. In the end of his
<hi>Caeſars</hi> we finde his Uncle <hi>Conſtantine</hi> conducted by the
Goddeſs <hi>Effeminacy</hi> to her Siſter <hi>Debauchery,</hi> where he
findes his Son <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi> making Proclamation as followeth;
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe words, though the Learned <hi>Loyolite
Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavius</hi> durſt not tranſlate to his Catholick Friends, I may to pious
Proteſtants without the leaſt offence, ſince they derive not their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51288:11"/> Religion from <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s
Biſhops, but from Chriſt immediately. <hi>Ho! whoſoever is either
Sodomite, Murderer, Rogue or Villain, let him dread nothing but repair hither,
with this water I'll make him clean in a trice: And if he ſhall happen</hi>
(as humane Nature is frail) <hi>to repeat the ſame Crimes, if he will but
thump his breaſt, and box his noddle, I'll warrant him as innocent as the
Child unborn.</hi> This was the vengeance <hi>Julian</hi> took for the
Barbarous Murders com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon almoſt his whole Family and Blood.</p>
            <p>Theſe particulars I thought fit to recount, omitting many
others, ſuch as the diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing and perſecuting men of honeſt and
Primitive Principles, free Learning and ſound Philoſophy, becauſe above
their Emulation; and paying devout Viſits to the Bones of dead Friars,
calling them <hi>Holy Reliques,</hi> and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. But that I may not be
thought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude my own Sentiments for <hi>Julian</hi>'s, I will adventure
to Tranſlate an Epiſtle of his to the Citizens of <hi>Bostra,</hi> who had
been in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, by reaſon, as it ſhould ſeem, of a
Toleration allow'd by <hi>Julian</hi> to the yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted Heathens of that
Town.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51288:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>JULIAN</hi> to the <hi>BOSTRENS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Thought verily the <hi>Galilaean</hi> Prelates would have
accounted themſelves better obliged by me, than they were by my
Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour. Since in his time many of them Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Exile,
Perſecution and Impriſonment; nay whole Corporations of them they term
Hereticks, were put to the Sword: Inſomuch that at <hi>Samoſata, Cyzicum,
Paphlagonia, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynia, Galatia</hi> and many other Countreys, whole Towns were
laid level with the Earth. The clean contrary to which has been in my time. For
ſuch as had been Exiled I called home, and to ſuch as had been
Proſcrib'd, I reſtor'd their own entire. But to that pitch of beſtial
Outrage are they arrived, that ſince they may not ſtill act the Tyrants,
nor as men above the controul of <hi>Laws,</hi> perpetrate what they did
formerly, not only upon us, that reverence the Gods, but upon one another too;
they leave no ſtone unturn'd, and have the impudence to raiſe Tumults and
Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions among the people; practiſing neither Piety to the Gods, nor
Obedience to our Laws, though ſo gentle and humane to them.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51288:12"/> Wherefore we will have none of them hal'd to
our Altars, but contrariwiſe do hereby ſtreightly charge them, that if any
of them ſhall hereafter of his free minde deſire to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate with us in
our Religious Rites, that he firſt offer Expiatory Sacrifice, and propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate
the averting Deities. So far are we from being fond of their communion, that it
cannot ſo much as once enter into us, that any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo impious as
they, can be at all qualified to participate of our holy Sacrifices, before he
hath purged his Minde by ſupplicating the Gods, and his Body by the uſual
Purgations. To me it is plain that the People, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of thoſe
they call <hi>Clergie,</hi> do raiſe theſe ſtirs, and all becauſe they
are reſtrained their former Exceſſes. For having once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd a Tyranny
of their own, they cannot be contented with Impunity for their paſt Crimes,
but ſtill thirſt for their former Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and becauſe they may not
play the Judges, nor make peoples <hi>Wills,</hi> and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs
themſelves of other mens Patrimonies, and ſo get all into their own
clutches, they leave no baſe nor unlawful deſign unattempted; but as the
Saying is, <hi>Pile fire upon fire;</hi> and are ſo daring as to adde to
their former Villanies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51288:13"/> freſh ones, much greater than them,
enraging the people, to create Diſorders. Wherefore I thought fit by this
publick Declaration to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn all good people, that they tumultuate not with
their <hi>Clergie,</hi> nor be perſwaded by them to take up ſtones, nor to
oppoſe their Superiours. Let them congregate with them as long as they
ſhall think good, and ſay what Prayers they ſhall appoint them, ſo it
be for themſelves only. But if they ſhall go about to Preach them into
Rebellion, let them give ear to them at their utmoſt peril. I the rather give
this warning unto the good Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Boſtra,</hi> becauſe Biſhop
<hi>Titus</hi> and his <hi>Clergy,</hi> to purge themſelves, have impeach'd
them; ſaying, That they had indeed done their utmoſt to qualifie them, but
that they were ungovernable. I have therefore ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in this my
Declaration the words the Biſhop had the face to inſert into his Defenſe;
<hi>Though the Chriſtians</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were not inferior to the</hi>
Greeks <hi>in number, yet I did my beſt to pacifie them.</hi> Theſe are
your Biſhops very words of you. Mark, I pray you, how he imputes your
quietneſs to himſelf, not to you. You are, if he ſay true, reſtrained,
not by your own good Inclinations, but by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51288:13"/> Expel him your City as your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Accuſer. You Lay-men live in peace one with another, and let none of you act
either Oppoſition to the Government, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice to your Neighbours.
Neither do you, abuſed and miſtaken people, offer any wrong to thoſe that
lawfully and truely ſerve the Gods according to antient Cuſtome; nor do
you, the true Worſhippers of the Gods, either mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Families or
ravage the Goods of thoſe that are miſled through Simplicity and
Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Men ought to be brought over by Reaſon and Perſwaſion, and
not by ill Uſage, Blows, or Stripes. I again and again ſtrictly charge all
ſuch as are Followers of true Piety, no wiſe to injure, affront or abuſe
the <hi>Galilaean</hi> Laity. For ſuch as act erroneouſly in greateſt
matters, are rather objects of Commiſeration than Hatred. Now as Piety is the
beſt of Goods, ſo is Impiety the worſt of Ills. And ſuch as
relinquiſh the Immortal Gods for the Bones and Reliques of dead men, are
ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently puniſht by the exchange they make. We ever compaſſionate
perſons involv'd in Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, as we congratulate thoſe whom the Gods
have deliver'd.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dat.</hi> Antioch.
<date>
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> 1.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51288:14"/>
               <head>The Epilogue.</head>
               <p>ALL pious Chriſtians will, I know, read the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties of this
unfortunate Apoſtate and Enemy of our true Faith, with juſt and due
abhorrence; but they will withal, I am perſwaded, admire to find the
Execrable Plots and Villanous Intrigues of the <hi>Roman</hi>
Eccleſiaſticks and their Dependents (not to charge one Old-man with the
common blame) ſo long ſince either truely exemplified or at leaſt
ſagaciouſly predicted, and that by a great Monarch of the greateſt Empire
the Sun hath yet ſeen: And not only theſe, but the intemperate and feeble
Paſſions alſo of the otherwiſe good men of our Times, who while they
pretend to inſtruct us, do themſelves under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text either of
Government on the one hand, or of Conſcience on the other, ſo ſhamefully
violate that grand and once indiſpenſable Precept of Charity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
them and us by our Saviour Chriſt. As if the Conteſt were not ſo much who
ſhould be moſt like to him, or moſt conformable to the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
delivered by him, as who hath moſt right to abuſe, Burleſque and expoſe
the reſt; and that perſon were moſt happy, who could procure a Priviledge
or Patent from God or Man for ſo doing. Let ſuch men read the Epiſtle
above, and bluſh at the equal candour and impartial Charity of a Heathen, and
for the future ſtudy to recover the Reputation of decay'd Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity by
better cultivating its Eſſentials, Piety, Loyalty, Charity, Sobriety and
mutual Forbearance. In fine, however Clergy differ in ſmaller points, ſuch
as School Subtleties, Rituals, Juriſdiction over us, Humour or Intereſt,
let not the honeſt Laity intermeddle, much leſs eſpouſe their Quarrels,
unleſs they ſhall deſire them, as in times of Primitive and Impolitick
Chriſtianity, to give their Suffrage among them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51288:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Irenicum Pag.</hi> 398. Repreſenting the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of
our firſt Reformers, concerning Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Politie.</head>
               <p>SOon after were called together by the Kings ſpecial or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
the former ſelect Aſſembly at <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle, where met (as
far as I can gueſs by the ſeveral Papers delivered in by every one of them
ſingly, and ſubſcribed with their own hands, all which I have peruſed)
theſe following perſons, <hi>Thomas</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,
Edward</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,
Edmund</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London, Robert</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Carliſle,</hi> Dr. <hi>George Day,</hi> Dr. <hi>Thomas Robertſon,</hi>
Dr. <hi>J. Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> Dr. <hi>Edward Leighton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Simon
Matthew,</hi> Dr. <hi>William Treſham,</hi> Dr. <hi>Richard Cozen,</hi> Dr.
<hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen Oglethorp,</hi> Dr. <hi>Thyrliby.</hi>
Theſe all gave in their ſeveral Reſolutions in Papers, to the Queſtions
propounded, with their Names ſubſcribed, (a far more prudent way than the
confuſion of verbal and tedious Diſputes) all whoſe judgments are
accurately ſummed up, and ſet down by the Archbiſhop of
<hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> himſelf. Their Reſolutions contain diſtinct
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to ſeveral ſorts of Queſtions propounded to them. The firſt
ſet contained ſeveral Queſtions about the Maſs, about the
Inſtituting, Receiving, Nature, Celebration of it; and whether in the Maſs
it be convenient to uſe ſuch Speech as the people may underſtand; whether
the whole were fit to be Tranſlated, or only ſome part of it; with
ſeveral other Queſtions of the ſame nature. The ſecond ſet is more
pertinent to our purpoſe, wherein are Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Queſtions propoſed to be
reſolved; Ten of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the number of Sacraments, the other Seven
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Church-Government. The Queſtions are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51288:15"/>
                  <hi>Q. 9.</hi> Whether the Apoſtles lacking
a higher power, as in not having a Chriſtian King, among them, made
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops by that neceſſity, or by Authority given them of God?</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10.</hi> Whether Biſhops or Prieſts were firſt;
and if the Prieſts were firſt, then the Prieſt made the Biſhop?</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11.</hi> Whether a Biſhop hath Authority to make a
Prieſt by the Scripture or no; and whether any other but only a Biſhop may
make a Prieſt?</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12.</hi> Whether in the New Teſtament be required
any Conſecration of any Biſhop and Prieſt, or only appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the
Office be ſufficient?</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13.</hi> Whether (if it fortuned a Prince Chriſten
learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to Conquer certain Dominions of Infidels, having none but the
Temporal Learned men with him) it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Gods Laws, that he and they
ſhould Preach and Teach the Word of God there or no, and alſo make and
Conſtitute Prieſts or no?</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14.</hi> Whether it be forfended by Gods Law, that if
it ſo fortuned that all the Biſhops and Prieſts were dead, and that the
word of God ſhould be there unpreached, the Sacrament of Baptiſm and others
unminiſtred, that the King of that Region ſhould make Biſhops and
Prieſts to ſupply the ſame or no?</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Whether a Biſhop or a Prieſt may
Excommunicate, and for what Crimes, and whether they only may Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate by
Gods Law?</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Queſtions, to which the Anſwers are
ſeverally returned in diſtinct Papers, all of them bound together in a
large Volume by Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and every one ſubſcribed
their Names, and ſome their Seals to the Papers delivered in. It would be too
tedious a work to ſet down their ſeveral Opinions at large; only for the
deſerved reverence all bear to the name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of that moſt worthy
Prelate and glorious Martyr,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51288:15"/> Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer;</hi> I ſhall
ſet down his Anſwer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to every one of thoſe Queſtions, and
the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of ſome others to the more material Queſtions to our
purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Ninth Qu.</hi> All Chriſtian Princes have
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them immediately of God, the whole cure of all their Subjects,
as well concerning the adminiſtration of Gods word for the cure of Souls, as
concerning the miniſtration of things Political, and civil governance.</p>
               <p>And in both theſe Miniſtrations, they muſt have ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
Ministers under them to ſupply that which is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their ſeveral
Offices.</p>
               <p>The Civil Ministers under the Kings Majesty in this Realm of
<hi>England,</hi> be thoſe whom it ſhall pleaſe his Highneſs for the
time to put in Authority under him; as for example, the Lord Chancellour, Lord
Treaſurer, Lord great Maſter, Lord Privy Seal, Lord Admiral, Mayors,
Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Miniſters of Gods word under his Majesty, be the
Biſhops, Parſons, Vicars, and ſuch other Priests, as be appointed by his
Highneſs to that Ministration; as for example, the Biſhop of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Dureſme,</hi> the Biſhop of
<hi>Wincheſter,</hi> the Parſon of <hi>Wynwick, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the ſaid Officers and Ministers, as well of the one ſort
as the other, be appointed, aſſigned, and elected in every place by the
Laws and Orders of Kings and Princes.</p>
               <p>In the admiſſion of many of theſe Officers, be divers
comely Ceremonies and Solemnities uſed, which be not of neceſſity, but
only for a good Order and ſeemly Faſhion. For if ſuch Offices and
Miniſtrations were committed without ſuch Solemnity, they were
never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs truely committed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51288:16"/>And there is no more promiſe of God, that
Grace is given in the committing of the Eccleſiaſtical Office, than it is
in the committing of the Civil. In the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, when there were no
Chriſtian Princes by whoſe Authority Miniſters of Gods Word might be
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, nor Sins by the Sword corrected; there was no remedy then for the
correction of Vice, or appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Miniſters, but only the conſent of
Chriſtian Multitude among themſelves, by an uniform Conſent, to follow
the Advice and Perſwaſion of ſuch perſons, whom God had moſt endued
with the Spirit of Wiſdom and Counſel. And at that time, foraſmuch as
Chriſtian people <hi>(mark)</hi> had no Sword nor Governour among them, they
were conſtrained of neceſſity to take ſuch Curates and Priests, as
either they knew themſelves to be meet thereunto, or elſe as were commended
unto them by others that were ſo replete with the Spirit of God, with ſuch
knowledge in the profeſſion of Christ, ſuch wiſdom, ſuch
converſation and counſel, that they ought even of very Conſcience to give
credit unto them, and to except ſuch as by them were preſented. And ſo
ſometimes the Apostles, and others unto whom God had given abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly his
Spirit, ſent or appointed Ministers of Gods word; ſometime the people did
chooſe ſuch as they thought meet thereunto, and when they were appointed or
ſent by the Apostles or others, the people of their own voluntary will with
thanks did accept them; not for the Supremacy, Imperie or Dominion, that the
Apostles had over them, to command as their Princes or Masters, but as good
people <hi>(honeſtly ſaid)</hi> ready to obey the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of good
Councellors, and to accept any thing that was neceſſary for their
edification and benefit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To Qu. 10.</hi> The Biſhops and Prieſts were at one
time, and were not two things, but both one Office in the beginning of
Chriſts Religion.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51288:16"/>
                  <hi>11.</hi> A Biſhop may make a Prieſt
by the Scriptures, and ſo may Princes and Governours alſo, and that by the
Authority of God committed them, and the People alſo by their Election. For
as we read that Biſhops have done it, ſo Chriſtian Emperours and Princes
have done it. And the People <hi>(mark this)</hi> before Chriſtian Princes
were, commonly did elect their Biſhops and Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12.</hi> In the New-Teſtament, he that is appointed
to be a Biſhop or a Prieſt, needeth no Conſecration by the Scripture; for
Election or appointing thereto is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13.</hi> It is not againſt Gods Law, but contrary
they ought in deed ſo to do; and there be Hiſtories that witneſs, that
ſome Chriſtian Princes and other Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men unconſecrate have done the
ſame.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14.</hi> It is not forbidden by Gods Law.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15.</hi> A Biſhop or a Prieſt, by the Scripture,
is neither commanded nor forbidden to Excommunicate. But where the Laws of any
Region give him Authority to Excommunicate, there they ought to uſe the
ſame, in ſuch Crimes as the Laws have ſuch Authority in. And where the
Laws of the Region forbid them, there they have no Authority at all. And they
that be no Prieſts may alſo Excommunicate, if the Law allow thereunto.</p>
               <p>Thus far that excellent perſon, in whoſe Judgment nothing is
more clear, than his aſcribing the particular Form of Government in the
Church to the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Supreme Magiſtrate. This Judgment of his
is thus ſubſcribed by him with his own hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. Cantuarienſ.</hi> This is mine Opinion and Sentence at
this preſent, which I do not temerariouſly define, but do remit the
judgment thereof wholly to your Majeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51288:17"/>Which I have exactly tranſcribed out of the
Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and have obſerved generally the Form of Writing at that time
uſed. In the ſame <hi>M. S.</hi> it appears, that the Biſhop of St.
<hi>Aſaph, Thyrleby, Redman</hi> and <hi>Cox,</hi> were all of the ſame
Opinion with the Archbiſhop, that at firſt Biſhops and Presbyters were
the ſame; and the two later expreſsly cite the Opinion of <hi>Jerome</hi>
with approbation. Thus we ſee by the Teſtimony chiefly of him, who was
inſtrumental in our Reformation, that he owned not Epiſcopacy as a
diſtinct Order from Presbytery of Divine Right; but only as a prudent
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Civil Magistrate, for the better Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the
Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus far the worthy Authour of</hi> Irenicum, <hi>to which I
ſubſcribe and conclude.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
